Charles Katerba, PhD

604 Somers Ave Whitefish, MT 59937 USA 406-241-5423 charles.katerba@gmail.com https://ckaterba.github.io

Professional Summary

Math professor and data analyst whose 10+ years of college teaching and research experience inform careful, precise analysis coupled with clear, concise communication. After building a strong foundation in statistical analysis and basic machine learning techniques, I am eager to start a new career in a more technical, modern data science role.

Skills

Technology: General:

R, SQL, Python, Tableau, git, LaTeX, Mathematica, SageMath, MS/Google suites Statistical analysis, regression techniques, traditional machine learning, clear and

engaging communication, problem solving and analytical thinking

Professional Experience

Oct. 2022 - Present Data Analyst (Part-time)

Flathead Valley Community College

Duties: Analyze student success data, fulfill ad-hoc data requests, develop and maintain Tableau dashboards, assist with IT integrations,

ETL projects, communicate findings, data governance/culture

Aug. 2019 - Present Associate Professor of Mathematics (Full-time)

Flathead Valley Community College

Duties: Teach a wide range of intro math/stats courses, develop intro stats curriculum, coordinate/manage dual enrollment courses/instructors, undergraduate research, advising

Aug. 2017 - May 2019 Postdoctoral Research Associate

Montana State University

Duties: Continue and broaden research program, teach undergraduate and graduate level courses, co-coordinate graduate math seminar,

co-organize directed reading program

Aug. 2011 - May 2017 Graduate Teaching Assistant

University of Montana

Duties: Teaching assistant and instructor of record for a variety of courses

Education

2013-2017 PhD - Mathematics

University of Montana, Missoula MT

Dissertation: Modules, fields of definition, and the Culler-Shalen Norm

2011-2013 MSc - Mathematics

University of Montana, Missoula MT

Masters Project: The Alexander Polynomial

2007-2011 BSc - Mathematics

Northern Arizona University, Flagstaff AZ

Minors: Philosophy, French

Data Projects

FVCC: No Holding Back Analysis [Investigate impact and equity of student holds]

Math and Chemistry Placement Test Analyses [Address need for co-requisite courses]

Enrollment Dashboard [Tool to explore current and forecasted enrollment]

Degree Audit Program [Tool that explores student degree progress]

Contract: Kalispell SD5 Enrollment Forecasting

Glacier High School Ascent Program Efficacy Analysis

Personal: Montana Scratch Lottery Scrape and Analysis

Local Avalanche Danger Forecasting with ML [In Progress]

Light-weight word predicting app [Coursera DS Capstone - In Progress]

Publications

Ideal points of character varieties, algebraic non-integral representations, and undetected closed essential surfaces in 3-manifolds. Casella, Katerba, and Tillmann. Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. **148** (2020), 2257-2271. Click for preprint

Modules, fields of definition, and the Culler–Shalen norm. Katerba. Submitted to Algebraic and Geometric Topology - revisions in progress. Click for preprint

Select Grants and Awards

Sept. 2022	NSF S-STEM Grant.	Award amount:	\$749,999,00.

Title: The STEM Core Experience: Fostering STEM talent through community

building and wellness support. Role: Former PI.

April 2017 NSF EAPSI Fellowship. Award amount: \$5,400.00.

Title: An Investigation of Closed Surfaces in 3-manifolds via Character. Varieties

June 2016 AMS Mathematical Research Community Fellow

Select Presentations

Nov. 2023	AI in the workplace. FVCC · Professional development seminar.
Aug. 2023	<i>Exploring enrollment trends.</i> FVCC · All employee in-service.
Jan. 2023	Data literacy: for who, for what? FVCC ·All employee in-service.
Mar. 2019	Searching for closed surfaces with character varieties. Utah State University
June 2017	<i>Modules, fields of definition, and the Culler–Shalen norm.</i> University of Sydney.

Professional Development

- Sage Days Duluth. Sage/SnapPy development workshop at UMN Duluth. June 2022.
- *StatPREP Workshop*. Strategies for incorporating *R* into intro stats courses. June 2021.
- *Data Science Specialization*. Coursera data science courses with R. 2021-2023.
- EDU291X. FVCC PD course for teaching online. Spring 2021.

References

Available on request.